Okay, the next section deals with pulmonary hypertension.
Recall that we have two independent circuits coming off the heart.
We've got a systemic circuit and we've got a pulmonary circuit.
Of course, the systemic circuit can undergo hypertension,
and we've discussed that in extensive detail in the vascular chapter.
And now we're going to focus a little bit, very briefly,
on pulmonary hypertension, or high pressure, within the pulmonary circuit.
Now, normally, the pressure in the pulmonary circuit is fairly low.
It's only about 10 millimeters of mercury.
However, were the pressure to increase, for example, beyond 25 millimeters of mercury,
that would then be defined as pulmonary hypertension.
Pulmonary hypertension is characterized by a few important pathologic changes.
You get atherosclerosis of the pulmonary trunk.
The idea here is that if there's high pressure on a vessel that increases the risk of atherosclerosis,
you're well aware of the fact that hypertension is a risk factor for atherosclerosis.
In addition, you get smooth muscle hypertrophy of the pulmonary arteries with some intimal fibrosis.
These are also classic findings.
And perhaps the most important on this slide are plexiform lesions.
This is what occurs when you have severe, long-standing disease.
And a plexiform lesion refers to a tuft or a group of capillaries that are placed together
that arise as a complication of long-standing pulmonary hypertension.
And I've circled a tuft of capillaries here on your slide.
When patients have pulmonary hypertension, this leads to right ventricular hypertrophy
because obviously the right heart has to pump against that high pressure in the pulmonary circuit,
and eventually the right heart can fail, which is called core pulmonale.
The classic presenting sign in patients with pulmonary hypertension is exertional dyspnea.
And were that to progress, they could eventually present with right-sided heart failure.
But here's the high yield.
If a patient presents with exertional dyspnea, especially a young woman,
you want to think about pulmonary hypertension.
Now that leads us to the etiology of pulmonary hypertension.
And remember that pulmonary hypertension can be divided into primary or secondary.
Primary, the etiology is unknown.
It's classically seen in young adult females.
And there is a familial form that's related to inactivating mutations of BMPR2.
That's high yield.
It comes up on exams.
When this gene is inactivated, you get excess proliferation of vascular smooth muscle.
And, of course, thickening of the blood vessel wall with vascular smooth muscle
would lead to pulmonary hypertension.
So again, high yield, BMPR2 inactivating mutations.
It's also possible to develop secondary pulmonary hypertension.
This could arise with hypoxemia.
You're well aware of the fact that the vessels in the lung, they constrict when there is hypoxemia
in an effort to try to shunt the blood towards other areas of the lung that perhaps maybe are
receiving oxygen.
However, in patients with COPD, for example, or interstitial lung disease,
there are no really good areas in the lung that are receiving oxygen.
And hence, the entire lung is clamping down, resulting in secondary pulmonary hypertension.
You also get secondary pulmonary hypertension with increased volume in the pulmonary circuit.
Now, when you put extra blood into the vessels, the vessels will undergo smooth muscle hypertrophy,
which will then result in pulmonary hypertension.
And the classic case here would be congenital heart disease.
And we've already discussed this in the cardiac chapter, in particular in the context of, for example,
Eisenmenger's syndrome.
A third way by which you can develop secondary pulmonary hypertension would be recurrent pulmonary embolism.
This is very high yield.
Let's go back and remind ourselves.
When patients get PE, there's several things that can possibly occur.
Most PE is asymptomatic, and that's because the lung has a dual circulation,
and most pulmonary emboli are actually relatively small.
So, again, the most common consequence of PE is that it's asymptomatic.
Of course, you can also get pulmonary infarction.
That would be a second consequence.
A third consequence would be sudden death.
That's classically seen with saddle emboli.
And remember that the fourth consequence of PE is where you have chronic, long-standing PE that get reorganized,
and that reorganization would result in thickening of the vascular wall,
which could then result in pulmonary hypertension.
And this is particularly high yield to be aware of as well.
And so if I had to summarize this particular section in just a few very high yield points,
I would say BMPR2 inactivating mutations, that's high yield,
and plexiform lesions as a consequence of that, that's particularly high yield.
And then don't forget that they get atherosclerosis of the pulmonary artery.
And so that's a quick summary of what are the super high yields in this particular section.
Moving on to respiratory distress syndromes, the first syndrome that we want to talk about is ARDS,
or acute respiratory distress syndrome.
The idea here is that you get damage to the alveolar-capillary interface within the air sacs.
Now, if there's damage to the alveolar-capillary interface,
this results in leaking a protein-rich fluid into the air sac.
The protein-rich fluid is eventually then reorganized as something called a highline membrane.
And that's the hallmark of this particular disorder,
the formation of highline membranes diffusely throughout the lung.
Here's an illustration of that.
You can see that these are the air sacs of the lung that I'm circling.
And you can see that each of the air sacs of the lung
is clearly lined by this dense pink highline membrane.
And, of course, that's the hallmark of ARDS.
Now, with the formation of these highline membranes,
two clinical problems are going to arise.
First of all, you've thickened the diffusion barrier for the exchange of gases.
And so the patients will not be able to exchange gas very well throughout the lung.
And as a result, they develop hypoxemia and cyanosis.
And that's the first problem.
The second problem with the development of highline membranes
is that these highline membranes are sticky
and will increase the surface tension of the alveolar air sac.
That's going to create a pressure on the alveolar air sac to collapse.
And so you're going to get diffuse collapse of the lung
as a consequence of the highline membranes as well.
So not only can you not exchange gas,
but you're not able to keep the air sacs open as well.
And that's why I say here in your text
that the clinical features are hypoxemia and cyanosis with respiratory distress.
Now, were you to do a chest x-ray on these patients,
you would see diffuse whiteout of the lung.
And that's a classic finding in ARDS.
There are multiple etiologies of ARDS.
In fact, were you to look at a list of causes of ARDS,
it would be in the hundreds.
But just as an example, sepsis can do it,
infection, shock, trauma, aspiration, pancreatitis, DIC, etc.
So multiple things can result in ARDS.
One of the underlying themes, regardless of the etiology,
is that there's activation of the neutrophils
with protease-mediated and free radical-mediated damage
of type 1 and type 2 pneumocytes.
And that's important to note,
that both the type 1 and type 2 pneumocytes get damaged in this disorder.
Now, the treatment involves addressing the underlying cause,
because, of course, that's the reason that the patient has gone into ARDS.
In addition, one of the key treatments for these patients
is going to be ventilation with positive end expiratory pressure,
also known as PEEP.
Now, the idea here is that the patients have collapse of their air sacs
due to the increased surface tension created by the highline membranes.
And so every time they breathe out, the lung collapses.
And then they have to place a tremendous stress on the lung
to be able to blow it open again.
And then again, when they breathe out, it collapses.
And then, of course, it takes a tremendous amount of energy
to try to blow it open again.
And so one thing that can be done on the ventilator
is that you can leave a little bit of pressure in the lung
at the end of expiration
so that those balloons stay open and don't collapse,
which then allows for recruitment of additional alveolar air sacs,
which then provides the patient with a chance to oxygenate that lung.
Now, it's important also to note
that recovery can be complicated by interstitial fibrosis.
This is particularly high yield.
And the reason you get interstitial fibrosis in the recovery
is because you knocked out your type 2 pneumocytes.
Now, remember that the type 2 pneumocytes are the stem cells.
And so when you knock out the stem cells,
you won't be able to regenerate the lung.
And instead, were recovery to occur,
it would be complicated by fibrosis
because, again, you would get repair instead of regeneration.
The next respiratory distress syndrome
is called neonatal respiratory distress syndrome.
This is respiratory distress that arises
due to inadequate surfactant levels.
Before you can understand this disorder,
you've got to take a step back
and just remind yourselves that surfactant is produced in the lung.
It's produced by type 2 pneumocytes.
That's particularly high yield.
Remember that the type 2 pneumocytes,
they have two functions.
They are the stem cell of the lung,
and they also produce surfactant.
Now, the purpose of surfactant
is to reduce the surface tension of the lung
so that when you breathe out, the air sacs don't collapse.
Let's just take a step back and remind ourselves.
If I were to bring a 7-year-old child in the room
and I were to ask that child to blow up a balloon,
it would be hard for the child to do so.
However, if I were to put a little bit of air into that balloon
and then hand it to the 7-year-old child,
they would be able to add air to the balloon.
So the hardest part of expanding a balloon
is that initial addition of air.
The same exact principle applies to the alveolar air sacs.
The greatest pressure required to blow open the sac
is in that very initial addition of air.
Now, of course, you don't want to have to spend
a tremendous amount of energy
blowing open the lung every time you blow out.
If every time you breathed out, the lung collapsed,
you'd have to spend a ton of energy blowing it open again.
And so the lung produces surfactant,
which decreases the surface tension,
leaving the air sacs open
so that the next time you breathe in,
you don't have to use a tremendous amount of energy
to breathe in.
Now, of course, if a patient has a lack of surfactant,
then every time they breathe in,
they're going to be using a ton of energy,
and they're very quickly going to develop respiratory failure.
And that's the idea in neonatal respiratory distress syndrome.
And so the key clinical features
that the patients are going to present with
are increasing respiratory effort after birth.
And that's because every time they breathe in,
they're using a tremendous amount of energy
to blow open the lung.
Now, eventually, that'll result in tachypnea,
use of accessory muscles
in order to continue to blow open the lung,
and grunting.
Eventually, of course,
the patients will develop hypoxemia and cyanosis.
And one of the key findings on chest x-ray
will be diffuse granularity of the lung.
Now, this is what the chest x-ray looks like.
And the idea here is that
if you were to look at the lung fields,
you can see that there's sort of this hazy granularity
or grainy appearance to the lungs.
And that's a classic finding
in patients who have
neonatal respiratory distress syndrome.
Now, the key causes of this disorder are three.
Number one, and most obvious, would be prematurity.
Remember that surfactant production
begins at about 28 weeks gestation,
and adequate levels are reached at about 34 weeks.
Now, if we have a preemie
who hasn't reached adequate levels,
of course, they're going to develop
neonatal respiratory distress syndrome.
Now, it's also very high yield to know
that you can screen for adequacy of surfactant
using something called the LS ratio.
The L stands for lecithin,
and the S stands for sphingomyelin.
And what you need to know here is that
as the lung matures from about 28 weeks to 34 weeks
as surfactant is being produced,
the key component in surfactant is lecithin.
And so lecithin will increase
from 28 weeks to 34 weeks, for example,
whereas sphingomyelin will stay constant.
And so as the lung increases production
of the lecithin component of surfactant,
that's going to then increase
the lecithin to sphingomyelin ratio.
And when the ratio is greater than two,
that indicates that the lung has now reached
adequate levels of surfactant production.
Very high yield to also know
that the major component in surfactant
is called phosphatidylcholine.
And by the way, phosphatidylcholine
is actually lecithin.
So sometimes the examiners will ask you,
what's the major component of surfactant?
Phosphatidylcholine, which again is lecithin,
which will increase as the lung matures.
And when the ratio of lecithin or phosphatidylcholine
to sphingomyelin is greater than two,
that indicates adequate lung maturity.
Another important risk factor is C-section delivery.
The idea here is that steroids,
they do a few things.
Number one, they increase the production of surfactant,
and number two, they cause surfactant
that is present within the type 2 pneumocytes
to be released into the lung.
And so that applies to this discussion
because when the baby is going
through the birthing process,
that's a very stressful period
to be contracted on by the uterine wall
and then to be pushed through the birth canal
creates a tremendous stress.
Of course, that stress results in release of steroids.
If a baby undergoes C-section delivery,
there is no stress,
and so steroids won't be released.
And so there's going to be an increased risk
of neonatal respiratory distress syndrome.
The final association is maternal diabetes.
The idea here is that if a woman has diabetes,
she's got a high blood sugar,
that high blood sugar is going to go into the baby.
And of course, the baby has a normal pancreas.
The baby's pancreas will respond
by producing excess insulin,
and insulin is an inhibitor of surfactant production.
So because the baby has high levels of insulin,
that's going to result in an increased risk
for neonatal respiratory distress syndrome.
Now, there are a few important complications to note
concerning neonatal respiratory distress syndrome.
The first is that hypoxemia present in the child
will increase the risk for persistence of the PDA.
Remember that the PDA closes
when there's good oxygenation of the blood.
And the second is that the patient would be at risk
for developing a necrotizing enterocolitis
due to the fact that there's decreased oxygen
going to the gut.
And the final complication is that
when patients are given supplemental oxygen,
as is classically used in treatment of this disorder,
that's going to result in increased production of free radicals.
Now, those free radicals can injure two major tissues.
The first is that the free radicals get in the blood,
and they can injure the retina,
which would then lead to blindness.
And the use of oxygen in neonatal respiratory distress syndrome
used to be one of the major causes of blindness in neonates.
In addition, remember that when a baby is born,
the lung is relatively immature,
and it takes a couple more years
for the lung to completely develop.
Now, if that immature lung is hit
with a tremendous amount of oxygen,
that would then result in excessive generation of free radicals,
and those free radicals would damage the lung
so that over time it wouldn't form properly.
And that's called bronchopulmonary dysplasia.
And so these are some complications to be aware of
concerning neonatal respiratory distress syndrome.
Thank you.